Emmanuel Evangelical United Brethren Church (Binghamton NY) Records
Emmanuel Evangelical United Brethren Church (Binghamton NY) Records
1877-1978
Emmanuel Evangelical United Brethren Church (Binghamton, N.Y.)
3.5 linear ft.
Established as the Emmanuel Church of the Evangelical Association in 1870 when the Reverend J. Vossler (Evangelical Association) was sent to Binghamton, N.Y., in response to the request of the people. After Feb. 1970, the name changed to the Emmanuel United Methodist Church; the church closed officially May 1976. Collection includes business files including, minutes of board meetings (in German) (1890-1899), trustees (1939-1940); Sunday school reports (in German) (1880-1910), and those of other internal governing bodies (1880-1976); financial records include cancelled checks, budget reports, and treasurers records (1914-1977).
148964
Biographical History
The movement which formed the Emmanuel Evangelical United Brethren Church was organized by Jacob Albright in Pennsylvania in 1800. He ministered mainly to the Germans in the area until, unable to obtain funding through the Methodist Episcopal Church with which they were associated, he established the Evangelical Association. They organized their first mission in New York (the Mohawk Mission) in 1839 and in 1849 held their first New York conference in Buffalo. Reverend J. Vossler was sent to Binghamton in April of 1878 upon request of the people there. They formed Emmanuel Church of the Evangelical Association of Binghamton ion March 2, 1870 with 24 charter members. The church was located at 80 Front Street, with the parsonage next door at 82 Front Street. Sometime after February of 1970 the name was changed to the Emmanuel United Methodist Church. It closed officially on May 13, 1976, and its congregation consolidated with other local Methodist churches.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Emmanuel Evangelical United Brethren Church Records consist of business files, financial files, and legal files. Business files contain records of different organizations within the church. Financial files contains the financial records of the church and of its various organizations. Legal files pertain to the sale of the church buildings after it closed.
Arrangement of the Collection
All series are arranged alphabetically by topic or subject.
Related Material
has several collections relating to churches in New York State. Please refer to for a complete listing. Also, our Rare Books collection has numerous related printed items; for a complete list of these, please search.
Subject and Genre Headings
Church and clergy; New York State; Vossler, H., Reverend.; Emmanuel Church of the Evangelical Association.; Emmanuel Evangelical United Brethren Church (Binghamton, N.Y.); Emmanuel United Methodist Church (Binghamton, N.Y.); Evangelical Association.; Church records and registers -- New York (State) -- Binghamton.; German Americans -- New York (State) -- Binghamton.; Methodist Church -- New York (State) -- Binghamton.; Methodists -- New York (State) -- Binghamton.; Minutes (administrative records); Reports.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Inventory
- Business files
  - Annual and board meeting minutes (in German), 1890-1899 (Box 1)
  - Board of trustees meeting minutes, 1939-1948 (Box 1)
  - Council of administration records, 1949-1976; 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Ladies Auxiliary Society secretary's records, 1931-1938 (Box 1)
  - Lists of elected officers, 1972-1973 (Box 1)
  - Local conference records, 1959-1963 (Box 1)
  - Official board meeting records, 1920-1949; 3 folders (Box 2)
  - Official church record book (in German), 1877-1916 (Oversize 1)
  - Official record book, 1921-1961 (Oversize 1)
  - Quarterly conference records, 1909-1923; 1947-1969; 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Reports, 1969-1976 (Box 3)
  - Sunday School secretary's records (in German), 1880-1882; 1899-1910; 3 folders (Box 3)
  - Unidentified records (in German), 1889-1920; 3 folders (Box 3)
  - Young People's Alliance records, 1905-1913 (Box 4)
  - Young People's Alliance roll call and dues records, 1894-1932 (Box 4)
- Financial files
  - Bank account records, 1968-1978 (Box 4)
  - Bills, 1974-1977; 4 folders (Box 4)
  - Cancelled checks, 1974-1976; 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Cancelled checks and check stubs, 1976-1977 (Box 5)
  - Check stubs, 1965-1976; 5 folders (Box 5)
  - Church accounts ledger, 1959-1976 (Oversize 2)
  - Conference remittance statements, 1975-1976 (Box 5)
  - Evangelical League of Christian Endeavor, treasurer's records, 1925-1945 (Box 5)
  - Final checking and savings account records, 1976-1977 (Box 5)
  - Financial report to members forms, 1966 (Box 6)
  - Proposed budgets, 1975-1976 (Box 6)
  - Reports, 1968-1976 (Box 6)
  - Savings accounts books, 1965-1975 (Box 6)
  - Savings accounts book, 1965-1976 (Box 6)
  - Statement of church assets, 1977 (Box 6)
  - Treasurer's records, 1914-1943; 1934-1937; 2 folders (Box 6)
  - Trustees' final statement, 1978 (Box 6)
  - Trustees' statement of disbursement of church assets, 1977 (Box 6)
- Legal files
  - Documents concerning ownership and sale of church land, 1972 (Box 6)